Register of the Aleksandr Sergeevich Lukomskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Sergeevich Lukomskii papers,
1914-1939
75008
Lukomskii, Aleksandr Sergeevich
4 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (1.7 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian military operations during World War I, and to the Russian Civil War. Also available on microfilm (5 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (5 reels).
Biographical Note
1914-15 Secretary of Imperial Russian War Office
1915-16 Assistant to Minister of War, in charge of Army Supplies, Imperial Russia
1916-April Commander of the 32nd Infantry Division, Imperial Russian Army
1916 Chief of Staff of the 10th Army and Director of Military Operations (Executive Assistant to the Chief of Staff) at Stavka, Imperial Russian Army
1917, April Appointed Commander of the 1st Army Corps, Imperial Russian Army
1917, June 16-September 12 Chief of Staff of the Supreme Commander-in-Chief, Imperial Russian Army
1917-19 Chief of the White Russian Volunteer Army under General Kornilov; Chief of Military Administration (War Minister) and Assistant Commander-in-Chief under General Denikin; President of the Special Council, or Government attached to the Volunteer Army; General Wrangel's representative at the Inter-Allied High Commission in Constantinople.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian military operations during World War I, and to the Russian Civil War. Also available on microfilm (5 reels).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Denikin, Anton Ivanovich, 1872-1947.; Kornilov, Lavr Georgievich, 1870-1918.; Russia. Armiia--Officers.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Dobrovol'cheskaia armiia.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1921-1939. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject File, 1914-1925. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, memoranda,reports, lists, maps, notes, printed matter, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Speeches and Writings, 1890-1934. (Box 2-4)
  Speeches, drafts,manuscripts (handwritten and typewritten), and notes, by Aleksandr S. Lukomskii, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Miscellany. (Box 4)
  Miscellaneous notes, memorabilia, printed matter.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1939 (Box 1)
  - Abramov, Fedor Fedorovich, 1937-38 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Anastasia, n.d. (Folder 1: 2)
  - Arkhangel'skii, Aleksandr, 1938 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Brinza, Madame, 1936 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Burtsev, Vladimir L'vovich, 1921 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Denikin, Anton, 1922, 1924, 1928, 1933-34 (Folder 1: 6)
  - International Center of Active Battle Against Communism (Brussels), 1938 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Krupenskii, A.N., 1928 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Kusonskii, Major General, 1921 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kutepov, A., 1924, 1928 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Main Directorate of the Union of Russian Invalids Abroad (France), 1939 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Metropolitan of Russian Orthodox churches in Western Europe, 1938 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Miller, Evgenii K., 1921, 1924, 1930-31, 1934 (Folder 1: 13-14)
  - Nicholas, Grand Duke, 1924-28 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1920 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Polovtzeff, Kirill A., 1937 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Tikhmeneff, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1939 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Union of Participants in the 1st Kuban March (Belgrade), 1927, 1932, 1937 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1: 20)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1925
  - Address book (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Brief Survey on Numerical Strength of the Russian Army" (in Russian), October 20, 1921 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Commission for Drawing-Up Means of Resistance Against "Soviet Dumping" in the Russian Emigration - Report (Komissiia Po Vyrabotke Mer Bor'by s "Sovetskim Dempingom" Sredi Russkoi Emigratsii - Doklad) (Folder 1: 23)
  - "Concerning the Murder of Former Emperor Nicholas II and His Family" (in Russian), by Minister of Justice Petukhov (Folder 1: 24)
  - Currency, Chinese and Japanese (Folder 1: 25)
  - Denkin, General
    - Excerpts from a speech, February 28, 1931 (in Russian) (Folder 1: 26)
    - Speech, May 22, 1917 (in Russian) (Folder 1: 27)
  - Guchkov, War Minister, response to his order by A. Lukomskii (Folder 1: 28)
  - Kirill Vladimirovich, Grand Duke (Folder 1: 29)
  - Maps (Folder 1: 30)
  - Maria Fedorovna, Dowager Empress of Russia, official response to Grand Duke Kirill Vladimirovich's proclamation of himself as Emperor of Russian (in Russian), October 4, 1924 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke, interview with E. Roberts (Associated Press), May 4, 1924, Paris (in Russian) (Folder 1: 32)
  - Passport (1924) (Folder 1: 33)
  - Production in Russia under the bolshevik government (1920) (Folder 1: 34)
  - Report to Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich regarding trip to Far East for possible anti-bolshevik movement, 1925 (in Russian) (Folder 1: 35)
  - Russian All-Military Union (Paris) (Russkii Obshche-Voinskii Soiuz) (Folder 1: 36)
  - "The Russian Army of General Wrangel Abroad" (in Russian), by Pavel A. Kusonskii, 1921. (Folder 1: 37)
  - Telegram from Headquarters to Petersburg (beginning of the revolution) (Folder 1: 38)
  - "To the Peoples of the World" (in Russian), by General Wrangel (Folder 1: 39)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1890-1934 (Box 2)
  - "Before the New European Catastrophe" (in Russian), 1922 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Beginning of the 'Democratization' of the Army in 1917 (in Russian) (Folder 2: 2)
  - Commentary on Colonel P.S. Mironov's article, "Mobilization Standards of Supply in the Russian Army" (in Russian) (Folder 2: 3)
  - Commentary on V. N. Kokovtsev's book, Out of My Past (in Russian), 1934 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Commentary on Iu. N. Danilov's book, Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich (in Russian), 1930 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Commercial-Industrial Rehabilitation in Russia" (in Russian) (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Dragomirov, General-Adjutant Mikhail Ivanovich" (in Russian), 1930 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Dragomirov, M. M. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Essays From My Life" ("Ocherki Iz Moei Zhizni")
    - Part I, "From First Childhood Reminiscences to the Graduation from the Petrov Poltava Kadet Corps" (in Russian) (Folder 2: 9)
    - Parts II and III (in Russian) (Folder 2: 10)
    - Part IV, "Kiev Military Region, 1897-1909" (in Russian) (Folder 2: 11-14)
    - Part V, "Period of Service in the Main Directorate of the General Staff and in the Office of the War Ministry, 1909-1914" (in Russian) (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "The Experience of War As Material for Preparation of the Troops" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Fire" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 3)
  - "The Forgotten Army" (in Russian and English) (Folder 3: 4)
  - Franco-Russian alliance (in French and Russian) (Folder 3: 5)
  - "General N. N. Golovin" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 6)
  - "I Think ..." (in Russian), clipping from Russkaia Gazeta, New York, July 16, 1933 (Folder 3: 7)
  - "In Memory of Lieutenant General Aleksandr Sergeevich Sannikov" (in Russian), 1931 (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Industrial and Commercial Restoration of Russia" (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Inspection of the Infantry" (in Russian), 1923 (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Intervention and Current Affairs" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 11)
  - "The Last Period of the World War, Agreement and Participation of Russia in the War (in Russian), 1923 (Folder 3: 12)
  - "The Luminary" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Memorandum" (in French and Russian) (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Monarchist and Anti-Socialist Movement in Europe"(in Russian), 1924 (Folder 3: 15)
  - "My Meeting and Conversation With General Vasili losifovich Gurko, January 27, 1928" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 16)
  - "My Non-Service Life in Petersburg Before the War and the Public Sentiments I came to Observe" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 17)
  - "My Skirmish With Lt. General Nechvolodov" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 18)
  - "Notes on Russia" (in Russian and English), October 1918 (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Operations of the 32nd Infantry Division During the Period From May 1 to September 15, 1916" (in Russian) (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Papers Relating to the Beginning of the Russian Revolution in 1917 and the Abdication of Emperor Nicholas II" (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "The Position Kept by France and Great Britain Toward the Fight Against the Bolsheviks in Russia" (Folder 4: 2)
  - "Preparation for the European War, Supply Shortage and Reasons for Failures on the Russian Front" (in Russian) (Folder 4: 3)
  - "The Proposed Sending of Russian Refugees, Taking Refuge in England, to Soviet Russia" (in Russian), 1921 (Folder 4: 4)
  - "The Red Army of Russia," September 14, 1923 (Folder 4: 5)
  - "Reminiscences" (in Russian), Part VI, Vol. I; Part VII, Vol. II (Folder 4: 6)
  - "The Russian Army Abroad" (in Russian), 1921 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "Russian Emigré Movement to America and First Impressions Upon Arrival in New York" (in Russian) (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Russian Immigration After the 1917 Revolution" (in Russian), 1924 (Folder 4: 9)
  - "Shatilov, General Pavel Nikolaevich" (in Russian) (Folder 4: 10)
  - "The Struggle Continues" (in Russian), 1936 (Folder 4: 11)
  - "The Struggle for the Renaissance of Russia" (in Russian), 1925 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Supplement to Chapter V (Folder 4: 13)
  - "Supply of the Russian Army and Country During the European War" (in Russian) (Folder 4: 14)
  - "The Supply of the Russian Army and Nation During the World War" (Folder 4: 15)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Folder 4: 16)
- MISCELLANY
  - Miscellaneous notes, memorabilia, printed matter (Folder 4: 17-18)